BU Records: Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee, Inclusive: 1934-1963, undated, Bulk: 1944-1954, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee
Inclusive: 1934-1963, undated, Bulk: 1944-1954, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/169
Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee
11 document boxes.
The BU Records: Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee consists of meeting minutes, correspondence, financial and legal records, as well as other documentation regarding fundraising efforts for and construction of the Tidwell Bible Building on the campus of Baylor University.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Plans to construct a building for the Bible Department at Baylor University began in Mineral Wells, Texas, in 1936 November, during the annual session of the Baptist General Convention of Texas. A group of 125 attendees met in the basement of First Baptist Church, where they discussed the construction of a new building on Baylor’s campus. Those present decided that the building should be named after Josiah Blake Tidwell, head of the Bible Department, to recognize his distinguished service to the university. The following year, architect Birch D. Easterwood designed floor plans for the proposed Tidwell Bible Building, which called for a two-story structure measuring fifty feet wide and 140 feet long. The building was to include three classrooms, a lounge room, office spaces, prayer rooms, a library with reading room, an assembly room, restrooms on a basement floor, and space for the Baptist Student Union Council.
Fundraising efforts slowed in the early 1940s because of construction restrictions during World War II. Work began anew in 1944 November, with the organization of a statewide fundraising campaign. Along with the renewed fundraising effort came the hiring of Guy A. Carlander, a prominent architect from Amarillo, Texas. Carlander was also the son-in-law of J. B. Tidwell. Carlander's new plan for the Tidwell Bible Building was for a ten-story building that included lecture rooms, offices, prayer rooms, a library, nursery, and a chapel that would seat 800. The most elaborate and prominent portion of the design was the 100-foot tall window that Carlander called the “wall of light.”
Ground for the Tidwell Bible Building was broken on 1949 May 28, but the structure would not be completed for several years. After Carlander’s architectural plans for the building were submitted to contractors for bids, the estimates greatly exceeded the $600,000 budget. When the committee asked Carlander to modify his design to reduce costs, Carlander refused. Subsequently, the committee relieved Carlander of his duties. In the summer of 1952, feeling that the university owed him more money than the $7,200 he had already received, Carlander sued Baylor for $109,000, a figure he based on the projected costs of the building he had designed. Despite a challenge to the lawsuit from the university in 1957 February, Carlander won and received $92,000 in 1958. Meanwhile, the campaign committee rehired Birch D. Easterwood to modify the building plans to fit within the budget. The finished structure, dedicated on 1954 October 22, rose to seven stories and cost just under $600,000.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee begins in 1934 and ends in 1963. Correspondence is the largest series in the collection and consists of numerous letters from the Tidwell Bible Building campaign committee regarding fundraising. The collection also contains campaign committee meeting minutes, as well as financial, legal, and promotional materials concerning construction of the Tidwell Bible Building.
Arrangement
An inventory of the BU Records: Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee existed prior to this finding aid. The collection items were loosely organized by material type.
Currently, the records of the BU Records: Tidwell Bible Building Campaign Committee are arranged in seven series: I. Minutes, II. Financial Records, III. Correspondence, IV. Architecture and Contracting, V. Promotional Materials, VI. Legal, and VII. Library.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/169. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
"Artist Presents Tidwell Building," Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1937 May 31.
“Baylor Challenges Carlander in Suit.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1957 February 1.
"Baylor Loses Suit in Tidwell Dispute." Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1957 March 20.
“Bible Building Ground Broken.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1949 June 1.
Bounds, Kara. "History of Tidwell Reveals Dispute Over Architecture." Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1988 September 30.
“Carlander, Amarillo Architect, Sues Baylor for $109 Thousand.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1952 August 6.
“Court Affirms Law Suit Against Baylor.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1958 July 11.
“Dedicatory Services For Tidwell Bible Building Scheduled.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1954 October 14.
“Drive to Raise Funds for Bible Building Starts.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1947 January 14.
“Dr. White To Be Featured At Tidwell Dedication.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1954 October 22.
“Guy A. Carlander Appointed Architect For Tidwell Building.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1944 November 24.
“Tidwell Architect Lawsuit Underway.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1957 March 7.
“Tidwell Bible Building Drive Amasses $215,000 Toward Goal.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1947 April 4.
"Tidwell Bible Building Site, Plans Revealed." Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1945 March 30.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Tidwell, J. B. (Josiah Blake), 1870-1946.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.
Subjects
Baylor University -- Faculty.; Church fund raising -- United States.; Historic buildings -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Building plans.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Minutes (Records); Reports.
- Minutes, 1945-1948; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of campaign committee meeting minutes from 1945 to 1948. It also contains meeting minutes from the Baptist General Convention of Texas from 1946.
  - Committee and Trustees Meetings, 1945, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of the Campaign Committee, 1947, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baptist General Convention, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Financial Records, 1936-1956, undated; 2
  This series contains financial records dealing with fundraising efforts and construction of the Tidwell Bible Building. Items in the series include pledge cards, donation and gift records, and financial reports.
  - Pledge Cards, 1936-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pledges and Requests, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chart for Distributing Pledge Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Donations Receipts, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - District Pledges, I-XII, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - District Pledges, XIV-XVII Combined, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Individual Gifts, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Individual Gifts, 1944-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - District Gifts, 1-4, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - District Gifts, 5-8, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - District Gifts, 9-12, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - District Gifts, 13-17, 1944-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Donations to Building Fund, Districts 1-4, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Donations to Building Fund, Districts 5-12, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Donations to Building Fund, Districts 13-17, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - District Totals to 1947 January 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - District Goals, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - District Chairmen, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Receipts for Expense Account, 1947-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Balance Sheets, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - R. A. Springer and Baptist Building, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - B. O. Herring, Financial Report, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial Report, circa 1947 March, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial Report Through 1947 July 10, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Financial Report Through 1947 November, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Financial Report, 1948 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Financial Report, 1948 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Financial Report, 1948 August 10 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fund Reports, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fund Reports, 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fund Reports, 1949 January-May (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fund Reports, 1949 June-December (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fund Reports, 1950 January-June (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fund Reports, 1950 July-December (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fund Reports, 1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Building Fund Financial Reports, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Building Fund Financial Reports, 1954 January-February (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Building Fund Financial Reports, 1954 March-May (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Building Fund Financial Reports, 1954 June-July (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Building Fund Financial Reports, 1954 August (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Building Fund Financial Reports, 1954 September-November (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Building Fund Rinancial Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fiscal Year 1951, 1950 August-December (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fiscal Year 1951, 1951 January-April (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fiscal Year 1951, 1951 May-August (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fiscal Year 1952, 1951 September-December (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fiscal Year 1952, 1952 January-April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Fiscal Year 1952, 1952 May-August (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fiscal Year 1953, 1952 September-December (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fiscal Year 1953, 1953 January-April (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fiscal Year 1953, 1953 May-August (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fund Reports, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1943-1954, undated; 3
  This series is the largest in the collection and contains many letters regarding fundraising efforts for the Tidwell Bible Building.
  - Thank You Notes, 1944 August-November (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Thank You Notes, 1944 December-1945 April (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Thank You Notes, 1945 May-July (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Thank You Notes, 1945 July-December (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Thank You Notes, 1946 January-June (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - First Baptist Church, San Antonio, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - District I, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - District II, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - District III, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - District IV, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - District V, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - District VI, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - District VII, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - District VIII, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - District IX, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - District X, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - District XI, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - District XII, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - District XIII, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - District XV, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - District XVI, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - District XVII, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Lists of Churches and Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Letters Received, 1946 December-1947 February, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Letters Received, 1947 March-April (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Letters Received, 1947 May (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Letters Received, 1947 June-July (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - M. L. Rhodes, 1947-1948 April (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - M. L. Rhodes, 1948 May-June (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - M. L. Rhodes, 1948 July-August (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - M. L. Rhodes to Church Treasurers, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - M. L. Rhodes, Letters Received, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - J. C. McKenzie, Letters Received, A-G, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - J. C. McKenzie, Letters Received, H-W, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - George C. Humphrey, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Guy Newman, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 January (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 February (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 March (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 April (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 May (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 June (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 July (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 August (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 September (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 October (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 November-December (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Guy Newman, 1950 January (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Guy Newman, 1951 February-March (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - O. D. Martin, Personal, 1947 January-March (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - O. D. Martin, Personal, 1947 April-June (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - O. D. Martin, Personal, 1947 July-December, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - O. D. Martin, A, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - O. D. Martin, BA-BL, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - O. D. Martin, BO-BU, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - O. D. Martin, CA-CH, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - O. D. Martin, CL-CU, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - O. D. Martin, D, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - O. D. Martin, E-F, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - O. D. Martin, G, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - O. D. Martin, HA, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - O. D. Martin, HE-K, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - O. D. Martin, L, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - O. D. Martin, MA-McC, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - O. D. Martin, McKenzie, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - O. D. Martin, RA-RH, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - O. D. Martin, RI-RU, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - O. D. Martin, T, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - O. D. Martin, U-WIN, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - O. D. Martin, WIT-Y, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - John B. Fisher, 1947 February-August (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - John B. Fisher, 1947 September-December (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - John B. Fisher, 1948 January-August (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - John B. Fisher, 1947-1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - John B. Fisher, A-B, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - John B. Fisher, C, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - John B. Fisher, D, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1944-1948 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1943-1954 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 April-August (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 September-November (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 December-1948 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Miscelleneous Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Guy A. Carlander, 1947-1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Campaign Correspondence, N-SHI, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Campaign Correspondence, SHI-SPE, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Campaign Correspondence, SPR-SU, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Neil C. Morris, 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Architecture and Contracting, 1953-1954, undated; 4
  This series contains construction proposals, building and mechanical contracts, and furniture and equipment specification documentation for the Tidwell Bible Building.
  - Construction Proposals, B-F, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Construction Proposals, H-J, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Construction Proposals, M-R, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Construction Proposals, S-Y, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Contract Document No. 1, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Contract Document No. 2, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Contract Document No. 5, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Mechanical Contract Document No. 1, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Mechanical Contract Document No. 2, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Mechanical Contract Document No. 3, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Mechanical Contract Document No. 4, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Mechanical Contract Document No. 5, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Specifications for Furniture and Equipment, circa 1954 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Specifications for Furniture and Equipment, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Promotional Materials, 1945-1954, undated; 5
  This series includes press statements and public relations items, campaign literature, advertising suggestions, and blueprints relating to the Tidwell Bible Building.
  - Promotional and Public Relations, 1954, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Press and Public Relations, 1950-1954, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Press Plate, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Blueprints and Word Picture, circa 1947 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Campaign Literature, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Campaign Literature, 1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Statements for Press, 1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Memorials, 1945, 1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Suggestions for Advertising, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Press Materials, Miscellaneous, 1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Dedicatory Service, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Legal, 1953-1957, undated; 6
  This series consists of legal documents relating to the lawsuit that Guy A. Carlander filed against Baylor University.
  - Deposition of W. R. White, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Baylor University vs. Guy A. Carlander, Argument for Appelant, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Baylor University vs. Guy A. Carlander, Appelant's Brief, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Baylor University vs. Guy A. Carlander, 1957, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Baylor University vs. Guy A. Carlander, Chronological Summary, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Library, 1934-1963, undated; 7
  This series contains documents regarding contents of and contributions to the Bible library formerly housed in the Tidwell Bible Building.
  - Bible Library Donations, Promotional Materials, 1938, 1940, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Tidwell Bible Library, 1959, 1963, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Bible Vault Collections, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bible Library Contributions, Anonymous and Compiled Lists, 1934-1943, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Bible Library Contributions, A-D, 1942, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Bible Library Contributions, E-K, 1941-1943, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Bible Library Contributions, M-R, 1943, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Bible Library Contributions, S-W, 1938-1943, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)